<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gem | Cristiano Betta &middot; Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://cristianobetta.com/blog/categories/gem/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cristianobetta.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-15T11:41:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://cristianobetta.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cristiano Betta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your mini-Heroku with Dokku and Dokkufy]]></title>
    <link href="http://cristianobetta.com/blog/2014/08/05/your-mini-heroku-with-dokku-and-dokkufy/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-05T22:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://cristianobetta.com/blog/2014/08/05/your-mini-heroku-with-dokku-and-dokkufy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've always enjoyed <a href="http://heroku.com">Heroku</a> but there are plenty of reasons both monetary and practical not to use it. I always liked the deployment method through Git though.</p>

<p>So this weekend at <a href="http://leedshack.org">LeedsHack</a> I started to look into <a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku">Dokku</a>, an open source mini-Heroku powered by <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a>, <a href="https://github.com/progrium/buildstep">Buildstep</a> and some other bits that share infrastructure elements with Heroku.</p>

<p>I found the installation rather tedious and as this was a hackathon I decided to create something simpler.</p>

<h2>Introducing Dokkufy</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cbetta/dokkufy">Dokkufy</a> is a Ruby gem that makes it super simple to set up your own mini-Heroku on your own server.</p>

<p>Simply install with a swift <code>gem install dokkufy</code> and you're ready to "dokkufy" both your server and your app.</p>

<h3>Part 1: Dokkufying your server</h3>

<p>Dokku only works with Ubuntu 12.04 and 14.04 server, so go get one of those images and boot up a server.</p>

<p>Then on your local machine run:</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cbetta/995577526584091c1e31.js"></script>


<p>As you can see this will ask you for a few details: server name or IP, username, and the eventual server domain to run all apps under. After a few minutes, depending on your broadband speeds, you will have a Dokku server ready do go.</p>

<p>Open up your server's domain or IP in a browser and voila!</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/2014/nginx.png" alt="Nginx" /></p>

<h3>Part 2a: Dokkufying your app</h3>

<p>Now that we have a Dokku server ready to go it's time to prepare your app.</p>

<p>I used the <a href="https://github.com/heroku/node-js-sample">Heroku Node JS sample app</a> for my example.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cbetta/50149a1b60d47ba91f28.js"></script>


<p>As you can see this simply asks for the details of your server and then adds a Git remote and writes a <code>.dokkurc</code> file to your app.</p>

<p>Now do a <code>git push dokku master</code> and you will see your app deployed.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cbetta/f5379254e1563f00c7ae.js"></script>


<p>Dokku will automatically create your project for you on first push and deploy your app to a subdomain of your chosen domain. In this case we deployed our app to <a href="http://node-js-sample.ppd.io">http://node-js-sample.ppd.io</a>.</p>

<h3>Part 2b: Controlling Dokku</h3>

<p>When you install Dokku on your server it gives you some handy commands. Sadly to run those from your local machine you need to perform some ssh-fu.</p>

<p>So to make this easier Dokkufy also comes with a local <code>dokku</code> command. You can use this command in any dokkufied app that has a <code>.dokkurc</code> file. It will automatically use that file to infer the remote server details and your app name.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/cbetta/b1ffe8aca4f571fbbd21.js"></script>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

<h3>Some final notes</h3>

<p>That's it for Dokkufy. I recommend running <code>dokkufy help</code> to see how you can explore and install plugins to install things like Postgres, Redis, and other features on your machine.</p>

<p>I also want to thank the awesome <a href="https://github.com/progrium">Jeff Lindsay</a> for his work on Dokku and I want to highlight what seems to be the next iteration of Dokku: <a href="https://flynn.io/">Flynn</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
